Have one of the shine. So, today we're
going to walk through Hermes Asian
harness and its loop engineering system.
This is one of the most popular harness
agent system right now and it's an open
source project. If you check the GitHub,
they've got more than 200,000 stars in a
very short period of time. So, it's
basically a self-improving AI agent
built by this research lab called neural
research and it's a built-in learning
loop. It creates its own skills from
experience instead of you telling the AI
like claw code to make skills and then
it also improves over time when you keep
using it because it persistently stores
knowledge in your local machine like a
MacBook. But anyways, this is all the
buzzwords. We're going to jump into this
Hermes agent system design like usual.
We're going to test it as well using
their desktop app. Just give you a quick
example. It's like a claw code, right?
You can see that it was thinking and
then it answered me in like a Pikachu
style. It said, "Pikapi, just hang out
in the my directory because it's
literally a bot living in my local
machine files. What are you building
fixing today? Pikapika." And also, you
can interact with it on WhatsApp and
then you say, "Good morning."
It's a little bit slow. I'm using a
Gemini 1.5 model for this. It took like
a good 5 seconds. And now it's basically
just using WhatsApp as the gateway to
receive information from my WhatsApp
account so I can just text it and then
ask it to do things for me. And say,
"Pikapi, good morning." You probably
realize that I've changed his
personality a little bit and there are
more interesting things I can show you.
For those who have watched my previous
agent harness loop engineering and
memory system, you might realize that
this chart is somewhat similar. This is
what the previous chart looks like. And
now if we look at harness or Hermes
agent again, I added a bit more
information, especially the difference
between the Hermes harness versus a
generic harness system. I marked the
differences in red. But we're going to
walk through this step by step. Also, I
prepared some testing examples to cover
harness, memory, skills, loop, gateway,
and LM ops or eval because a lot of
people were asking me if I could
implement some real examples. So, here
we are. Without further ado, let's jump
right in. Okay. So, firstly, let's look
at the foundation of Hermes harness
agent. It's a harness that runs on your
local machine. You can use either local
command lines, Docker, SSH, or a virtual
VPS. There are two main ways to interact
with Hermes agent. One is using your
favorite communication apps, and in my
case, I used WhatsApp, or you can just
use your desktop app with the Hermes
agent. So, you can come to Hermes
official website,
hermes-agent.newresearch.com,
and just click on download for Mac OS,
or you can click on Windows over here to
use the command line to install it.
Essentially, it's still a chatbot, just
like Clawcode, and then you ask the
question to either the communication app
or the desktop version. It's very
similar to open claw, where you can use
WhatsApp to control it. So, after user
sends the prompt, the user prompt with
the current chat history and the system
prompt will be fed into working memory,
and then this LLM agent is basically the
Hermes agent that will be answering your
question. And it will be using a loop
engine over here to call up some tools
that are only on Hermes. And eventually,
after finishing the task, it's going to
end the loop and then send the user a
reply. Just literally sending a question
throughout this entire ephemeral agent
run, and then get the user reply, just
like my Hermes was greeting me like a
Pikachu. And by the way, how did this
happen? Right, I'll show you right now.
So, the system prompt for Hermes is
interesting. It's called soul.md. I
really like how they name it. It says
soul. If you come to the right-hand
side, you can see there's a little file
bar, and this is your local files, and
you can go find out there's a dot Hermes
folder, and we open that, and we scroll
down,
you will see there's a file called
soul.md. Double click on that,
and you can edit this yourself, right?
But since I've already edited it, after
you edit anything, you can just click on
save. I basically said you talk like
Pikachu. Every reply starts and with
pika pika pika p. If you are excited,
say pika p with the lightning. If you're
sad, say it quiet pika. I'm pretty sure
you can do something similar in Clawcode
for this. In Clawcode, something similar
would be in customize,
general, and you can see there's an
instruction for Claude. You can tell
Claude to do certain things and not to
do some things. It's basically the
system prompt used across the entire
agent harness. If you didn't watch my
previous video on harness and loop
engineering, harness is basically a set
of tools that allows you to control over
this really powerful horse, which is the
LLM itself. In our case, the LLM we're
using is Gemini because I've got the
Google credits. I don't want to burn my
Anthropic credits, but feel free to use
Anthropic. This is the This is the agent
of the the horse, and the harness is
this entire thing. It's like a horse
harness that you ride on, and you make
sure that the horse is not going
anywhere random and it's using the tools
accordingly to move in the right
direction. Harness is a very vague
concept. Just don't fantasize it. It's
nothing complicated. It's just a
buzzword. Now, we're going to continue
to build up this harness right here for
Hermes, but what I'm going to show you
is what a loop is. The concept of loop
got really popular because these days
people build a lot of agents. You don't
want to always tell the agent what to
do. You want the agent to figure out
what kind of prompt it should send, what
kind of tools it should call. Let's take
a look at what tools Hermes agent
actually have to enable this loop
engineering. We're going to cover this
briefly, and then I'll show you real
examples. So, first of all, the agent of
Hermes is having a set of tools that
include the terminal, the browser. Okay,
you can use your laptop's terminal. You
can start browser. It can delegate task,
which means that it can spawn up some
sub agents for you. For example, you can
ask it to spawn up an agent which will
call your claw code CLI to write code
for you. If the task is basically fixing
some bugs on my GitHub. And then it can
schedule cron job. A cron job is
basically it can schedule something that
will happen at certain time. You don't
need human intervention to do it. For
cron job, let's just try right now. In
Hermes agent, I can say, "Help me set up
a cron job that will tell me a Pokémon
joke every minute in the next 10
minutes." Okay, I'm just going to send
this.
And also, I'm going to send this to our
Hermes agent WhatsApp interface, too.
Instead, I'll just say, "Tell me a
developer joke every
It just quickly called this a cron job,
and it says repeats 10 times for the
next 10 minutes. Because it says it's a
thing in the terminal UI, it won't be
able to print it. So, I need to ask it.
I just ask like, "What's the first
joke?" And you can see on WhatsApp it
also got scheduled. The Chrome it says
the joke machine is powered and
scheduled. Uh I've set up a cron job to
send you a fresher joke every minute in
the next 10 minutes. You should receive
the first one in about a minute.
We'll see about that. Okay.
Uh why did the Squirtle cross the ocean?
To get the other tide. Pika pika. Okay,
so that was cron job. It can do skill
management as well. It can connect to
MCPs as well. It depends on the question
that the user asks. The agent will just
leverage these tools until it's done and
then it will send a reply to you. Okay.
The example we just saw was cron job.
I'm going to show you some more examples
later, too. Let's test a few harness and
loop examples. The first one is use a
terminal tool to find out what OS
version I'm on and read the last 10
lines of my shell history. Let's do
that. Let's start a new session.
I'm just going to ask this exact
question to it. So, you can see it ran
this on my local machine and then it
figured out that I'm on Mac OS 26.5.
And the last 10 lines I used in shell
history is basically text uh get status
get status get status. I always like to
check get status. And here what happened
was that it ran through this agent run
and then it called the terminal to do
the task for me. Which is checking what
system I'm on. This is a very simple
example, but you can do more crazy
things. You can ask it to use the local
machine terminal to do things for you.
If you're using Clockwork, you're you're
very familiar with this already, all
right? There's nothing special about it.
I'm just showing you the example that
this is a harness and there's a loop
because after I fetched it, it will stop
and tell me and reply to me. Let's look
at the cron job as well. You can see
that it sent me two jokes already.
Why do Java developers wear glasses?
Because they don't C#. Pika pika. I
would tell you a UDP joke, but I have
absolutely no guarantee that you would
get it. I'm not going to wait for
acknowledgement anyways. Pika.
Okay, this one I didn't get it. So, one
more example. browse to YouTube channel
Shawn's AI stories, title plus views my
last videos, create new video titles for
this current video I am filming. So,
here we're we're asking it to use the
browser basically. Okay, you can see
that it started doing the searching. All
these things already exist on Clockcode.
I'm just explaining it from a system
design perspective and showing you
examples, okay? And then also, I will
show you what's the difference between
Hermes and Clockcode. So, please bear
with me. All right, so I need to run a
Python script. can see it also used some
of the clicking tools. Oh, there's an
error. The website was wrong.
Try this new one.
It saved a little memory here, okay? It
said the user profile updated. This is
something I'm going to cover in a bit,
but spoiler alert, Hermes agent will
save agent memories by itself. It's
basically in your local files, too. If
you come here, within the Hermes folder,
if you scroll down, in memories, you can
see there's a memory.md. If we double
click on that, it stored YouTube here,
each of scraping quirk. So, because it
realized that it had a mistake, so it
updated itself with a memory. This is a
self-iterating process of this harness.
Good, so it read my previous YouTube
titles. It realized that I've got this
video that's got 100,000 views, and
since I'm filming a new video now, it
gave me some new titles. So, what
happened here was the user, which is me,
who asked the question through the
desktop, and then it went through this
agent run, and then this agent harness
Gemini that I'm using was basically used
calling the browser right here to search
up my YouTube channel. And then it came
back and said, "Hey, it didn't find
anything." So, uh it basically stopped.
There's an end loop guardrail. The
guardrail stopped and said, "It didn't
find anything." So, I realized that,
okay, the previous URL was wrong, so I
input it again.
Uh it called the browser again, and it
also called the terminal to run some
Python script, and because it needed to
do some task, and eventually it came
back with the answer. There's a
mechanism that says, "Okay, end the
loop, no more tool calls, and send the
answer." These are two quick examples of
what a hard is loop engineering is. You
see, you're already using it every
single day. It's nothing fancy. So,
don't get overwhelmed next time when you
hear these terms. It's just a buzzword.
So, what happened just now was this
memory.md that we saw regarding YouTube
memory, Hermes agent after or during the
agent run is going to start to create
its own skill.md and memory.md depending
on if it's feeding into the procedure
memory or if it's feeding into the
semantic memory. We should add one more
arrow here, basically. So, essentially,
the way that Hermes agent works is that
it's storing its own skills and memories
completely locally. Nothing's stored in
the cloud. It has its own self-improving
loop. Every time when it realized that
something is a mistake that it should
learn from or it's a repeated task, it
will start to summarize, "Okay, here's
some new memories I should know for the
future in order to serve this user
well." It started to save these files
into these two chunks of memory system.
First one is called procedure memory.
It's basically how you act, how the
Hermes agent should be acting, and it's
usually saved in this directory called
Hermes skills skill.md. Hermes skills
and any of these, okay? Autonomous AI
agent, claw code, there's a skill for
how Hermes will use claw code here. So,
it will basically delegate any coding to
claw code CLI. Shows you exactly how you
should do it, like install Claude, run
it, and do the authentication and all
these kind of things. And what we just
saw earlier was memories. Memory.md is
saving the semantic memory, which are
some durable facts or things related to
the user profile. So, if the user has a
habit or has some important facts or
information it should remember, then it
will be saved in the memory.md. And then
what's interesting is that for Hermes,
instead of doing the embeddings, it's
actually just using plain text, okay?
It's using top top K keyword instead of
doing the embedding or the rack system.
It's very interesting because I'm not
too sure why, but it's just doing the
text. So, remember that we say the agent
run is ephemeral. Now that with the
working memory to be fed into the agent
for all the loop engineering,
which includes procedure memory,
semantic memory, and later we'll cover
episodic memory, this will become a more
complete memory system that will feed
into the agent runs, which is making the
harness more elegant. And the third
pillar that we haven't covered is called
episodic memory. It's basically the chat
history or some dated events. It can be
ragged or sequeld into the working
memory. After every agent run, the
information will flow into the episodic
memory. What's different in Hermes is
that the data is not saved in the cloud.
It's saved in this place called
state.db. Again, let's come back here.
On the right-hand sidebar, if we again
open Hermes folder, scroll down, you can
see at the end there's a state.db.
I can click on preview anyway. This is
basically a database that will include
all those info in your chat history, but
also over time it will start to
consolidate some of those chats using
the Hermes auxiliary models, which are
cheaper, non-important models to do this
summarization task so that it will
distill some facts into what we call the
semantic memory or that memory.md. So,
you can see this harness is running
really in a self-improving autonomous
situation, which is really cool. I know
this chart is getting more complicated
than usual, but I feel like this should
be a complete summary for how the Hermes
agent works. And let's go through a few
more examples. Let's test out some of
the stuff for memories. Save to memory
that my favorite testing framework is
pytest. So, this is an explicit saving,
all right? It updated the memory file.
So, if we go to memory,
you can see one more block, which is
user's favorite testing framework is
pytest. That was an explicit ask from
the gateway. The tool is basically,
let's go update the memory over here.
Search our past sessions. What was the
very first thing I ever said to you? Now
it's using the searching tool in the
loop engineering iteration. Say the
first thing I say is, "What can you do,
Hermes? And what makes you special?"
Let's double-check that. That's right.
And it failed because I couldn't log in
at that time. So, what happened was I
asked the question through the
interface. It went through the prompt.
And in the working memory, because we
asked that, so it queried the
information from episodic memory, from
state.db. It returned the memory into
the agent. The agent was like, "Oh,
okay. This is what you said." Let's try
an example related to skills, which is
procedural memory. So, we're going to
say, "Create a skill called video prep
that captures how I format my video
scripts spoken in English, define jargon
on inline, no m-dashes, closes with you
can build anything, you can learn
anything." This is an explicit call to
update the skills. It used the skill
management tool. Remember, in the loop
engineering, there's a tool called skill
management, and this is what it did. And
say, "Pick-a-P, I have successfully
created the video prep skill. Let's find
out about it." Again, Hermes, skills,
media,
video prep. Double-click. It created
this skill for me. It says, "No
m-dashes, spoken English, define jargon
inline, catchphrase, you can build
anything, you can learn anything." Good.
We can test the loop a little bit more.
We can say, "Use delegate task to spawn
two sub-agents." One is researching the
LM eval harness, and another one
researching VLM architecture. The agent
was calling the tool called delegate
task, and successfully spawned two
background agents. So, you can see it's
processing right now over here. They're
working in parallel.
Cool.
Eventually, we returned the results to
me. So, you can see that it spawned up
some sub-agents to do tasks for me in
parallel. We've already tried the cron
job, and next one is spawn sub-agent
that uses Claude CLI. This is my
favorite. So, this is my favorite. Spawn
a sub-agent that uses the Claude CLI in
headless mode, basically using Claude to
build a Python script fetching the top
five Hacker News stories to markdown,
and verify runs.
Yep. It firstly delegated the task to
Claude CLI. It's using the skill, you
can see. Remember we read the skill here
in autonomous AI agent Claude. It should
be reading the skill. Is this helpful?
Let me know if this is helpful. I mean,
I was trying to show you more examples
in the walk through so that it feels
more concrete because a lot of people
were asking me for implementations from
my previous videos and I feel like
Hermes is really good example.
Okay, it created this
code for me and used the Claude.
It created the fetch hackernews.py.
I'll just say show me the
result after
running the script.
Yep, so these are the top five Hacker
News stories on Hacker News. Let's come
check. It's correct. Remember what
happened was that we sent the question
from the gateway, it went through the
agent run and the LLM basically called
up the tool called delegate task.
Delegate task delegated the task to sub
agent and the sub agent was running
Claude code and Claude code wrote that
script and sent it back. And then this
agent run the script again and then we
get the results. This was the hardest in
the loop engineering in this entire
thing. I don't think it self-triggered
self-learning skills yet. It only
triggered learning the memory. I'm just
going to ask it explicitly, did you save
any skills by yourself or did you only
save memory so far? Oh yeah, but we
created that but we created
that skill.
You did not self- realize
you need to save skill.
It should proactively offer to save a
skill after difficult iterative task
with five or more tool calls. So far we
haven't done anything difficult. So we
can test the gateway.
I can summarize what we worked on today.
Hmm, this Chrome job failed. It didn't
tell me 10 jokes, it only told me two.
What were the
rest of the jokes?
Don't lie to me because maybe you just
created it. Anyways, Hermes team if
you're watching this, your Chrome job is
not updating it unless I ask for the
results. So, maybe this is something you
guys can fix. All right, let's move on
and summarize what we worked on today
because in this current chat, it doesn't
know the rest of the stuff here. So,
let's see if it's calling the actual,
remember we say state DB, memory.md, and
skills.md. Good, actually knows, okay?
It says jokes on demand, system check on
the OS version, which is what we did,
YouTube stats, yes, we did that, Hacker
News. Okay, good. WhatsApp here is just
a gateway as an interface. It's doing
the same thing as the Hermes agent
desktop. This is very cool. This is I
mean, this is similar to Open Claw, but
still every time when I feel I can just
have a personal assistant handy on my
WhatsApp, this is really cool. And
imagine if I host this on a virtual
machine and it runs forever, I can just
basically ask WhatsApp, what's going on?
And it's going to reply to me. Ooh, I
completely forgot. You should set up
WhatsApp by typing in Hermes WhatsApp
and then just follow the instructions to
set it up. Should be straightforward.
Last but not least, where is eval? Okay,
where is our LLM ops? Remember in our
original chart we had this blue box on
the right-hand side called LLM ops. So,
unfortunately, on Hermes, based on my
current research, I don't think it has
an LLM ops or an eval system. You'd
probably need to build it yourself. But,
it does trace the run. There's a thing
called trajectory export and logs and
it's basically just logging the whole
thing, but there's no eval. If you
watched our previous video, the eval is
basically you can use tools like Line
Smith, Line Fuse, and all these things
that can track the entire agent run and
some events that happened like tool
calls, how many times did you call LLMs,
did you use some cheaper models to
summarize things into a semantic memory?
Unfortunately, Hermes doesn't do that.
I'm curious why, maybe because it's a
local system, so you can just customize
it yourself. It's under Hermes, you can
click into logs, you can see all the
logs here, can see the errors, can see
the agent runs, gateway logs, too.
Gateway is the entry point, which is
WhatsApp or this desktop. I hope this
was helpful. I think there's quite a
huge amount of work that we covered
today, which are exactly what Clawcode
can already do or Open Claw can already
do. I feel that what makes Hermes
special, at least compared to Clawcode,
is that it's self-updating all these
things locally. And maybe this is good
for privacy reasons, because I don't see
why we should not save it on the cloud.
Other than that, everything else should
be very similar, right? It runs the loop
every time when the agent needs to do
some task, kind of call all these tools,
and you can even schedule cron job. And
then the memories and the skills are
getting auto-updated into the procedure
memory, semantic memory, and the state
data will be saved into the episodic
memory. So, I would say this is a pretty
standard harness for an agent
implementation. Nothing too fancy, but
I'm sure they did a ton of work. But I
feel like this is a good example of for
how builder these days should be
building products, because this is
becoming a standard, right? Every AI
agent tool should be self-improving and
self-evolving. And depending on the user
request, you can either keep it local,
you can keep it on the cloud. That's up
to you. I feel like the skill and memory
accumulation is probably the most
valuable thing in this, because the user
kind of just over time get locked in.
And it remembers who I am, which is why
like recently I don't switch to other AI
anymore. I just use Clawcode. It has a
semantic memory about who I am, my
company information, Automata's, and
what my style of building YouTube
videos. But yeah, I think it's a cool
framework. You guys should try it out.
It's really fun. Cool. I hope this video
was helpful. If you have any questions,
please leave down a comment. And if you
enjoyed it, please give me a like and
subscribe. Let me know what else you
would like to watch. I will see you next
time. Thanks.